Phillip: Hi I’m Phillip
Maddy: And I’m Maddy
Knowing how to create and maintain an effective
team is an important part of team leadership.
Phillip: But it’s important to realise that
the evolution of teams and their good running
isn’t always a clear and linear process.
It can often be unpredictable
and can even be a little chaotic!
Using a model is a good way to prepare for
the likely events you’ll encounter, but
there’s always going to be some small distance
between the content of the model and reality.
Let’s look at the Tuckman’s team development
model and some of the general principles around
creating and maintaining an effective team
Maddy: Tuckman’s model is really
helpful for plotting out the evolution
that a team goes through, and it
breaks this down into four main steps:
• Forming
• Storming
• Norming
• Performing
There is also a fifth step called Mourning
which is also known as adjourning.
Let’s look at these in more detail.
Phillip: Forming refers to when
the team starts to come together.
There’s a lot of uncertainty at times
so strong leadership and clear goals
are especially important at this point.
Maddy: Storming is when the work has begun.
The team now must reckon with reality
and will inevitably experience
resistant of some kind or another.
Team members will also be working with one
another, and this will probably produce
some conflicts and raise some problems too.
Phillip: Norming is when the team
has started to get its act together.
Differences within the team are being
reconciled, realistic expectations around
team goals have been established, and
the real work is finally being done.
Maddy: Performing is when is the team at its peak.
It’s working as a well-oiled machine, hitting
its targets, and operating efficiently.
Phillip: Mourning the fifth step refers to
the point when a team is being wound down.
Some teams may not go through this step and
continue indefinitely, but ones that reach an end
point, for whatever reason, will undergo a period
of reflection and probably a little sadness.
Maddy: Tuckman’s model is useful as
it covers the whole team lifecycle,
and it gives you the landmarks of team
development and maintenance to look out for.
By regularly reviewing how your team is
functioning, you can determine which of
the Tuckman’s stages have been reached,
as well as the next steps you need to take
to develop your team onto the next level.
But remember that this isn’t always a linear
process and teams can go “backward” as
well as “forward”, going down to a previous
level, instead of onwards to the next.
Phillip: Let’s look at some more general
principles for creating and maintaining a team.
It is important to make sure that the
team’s purpose is clearly defined.
This might be a one-off project, or
it could be permanent working group.
Whatever it is, it should be made clear,
because it will affect your choices when
it comes to choosing the right people.
Maddy: So, who are the right people?
You should try and find a balance of
fresh perspectives and experience.
Look out for people with
the right skills and talent.
Also, you should think hard about the
pool you’re drawing from, do some of
the people work better together or
maybe they should be placed with others?
These are important factors to consider.
Phillip: Make sure you schedule regular reviews
and catchups, so that everyone is clear on
their duties and responsibilities, but not
so regular that they become a nuisance.
Maddy: And finally, it’s really important,
that you have multiple channels and
methods for giving and receiving feedback.
Your team should develop a culture of giving
each other feedback, with some kind of formal
process around this, especially when it comes
to giving feedback about team leadership.